hi everyone welcome back in another
Amazing Project where we're going to be
building this task manager application
so before I start showing you the
application I want just I want to just
let you know that I I was heavily
inspired by this uh lot of small
application provided by Shad CN to be
able to show uh the components but also
to be able to show the react table
so this is what they're using to be able
to actually uh use this table with all
the features that we're going to be
using like sorting filtering and other
things uh that we're going to be using
for the application and we're going to
learn through building this application
so as you can see here we're having a
simple nav bar at the top we're having
the lights and dark mode so it's pretty
straightforward we're using uh Shad SC
for this we're having the dialogue to be
able to add uh or edit uh a tack I'm
going to show you how this is working
we're having these cards to be able show
to be able to show some numbers so here
in the text or the table area we're
having the filter so uh if I want to
look for something as you can see I'm
going to get uh what I'm searching for
but if I don't find anything so we are
going to get this message all of this
we're using uh react table also we
can be able to actually um show uh the
states of the test with their numbers so
it is pretty much the same like uh
they're having in here so we're going to
build this from scratch so when I click
on the too so I'm going to just get the
tasks that uh are uh having the to-do
stages also notice right now uh we can
be able to show uh the actual uh filter
tag that we clicked on so the same thing
that it is happen happing in here so
when I click on the other one we're
going to show it uh uh next to it so the
same think it's going to happen if I
click on the
backlog and also we can be able to
really filter down uh stuff when I click
on medium So eventually uh because we
are already filtering by States uh
there's uh no tou that match the
filtering uh the filtering elements that
we selected but when I click on low so
we're going to get the two tasks because
uh it matches uh the the filtering that
we set and when I click on the reset so
everything it's going to be reset and
also we can be able to actually hide the
columns as you can see and uh also we
can be able to do it just from here so
if I had the stitches gon and here as
you can see it's going to be and shcked
automatically so and all of this is
going to be handled by tack react table
and also we can be able to sort dently
and accidently and decid and also we can
be able to do this for the other columns
but as you can see the title doesn't
have the hide features because if we
hide it we can't be able to filter uh
the elements because we're using this
colum for the filtering and if this is
hidden we can't be able to do the
filtering so that's why we uh enabled
the hiding for the title
column and uh finally we're having at
the bottom the bination as you can see
so everything is working as expected so
now I'm going to show you this little
drop down so this drop down I was
inspired by the same drop down but I
added some icons just to make the drop-
down pop a bit and all of the features
in here so now nothing is working but
here everything is working so I'm going
to start by making a copy for
example when I click on make
copy so as you can see the actual uh
task has been copied
successfully and if I want to delete
this task all I have to do click on the
delete and as you can see the task has
been deleted successfully with the
notification now if I want to set it as
has favorite or unfavorite so uh the
thing that I added though is the
favorite so I can be able to set for
example this task as favorite so when I
click on favorite so it's going to be
set as favorite and this it's going to
be changing dependent on whether it is
favorite or not so if it is favorite
it's going we're going to show the INF
favorite text otherwise we're going to
show the
favorite and here we can be able to
actually uh Define or update the the the
bug uh the label story just from here so
the same thing if we do for this
application so I'm going to set it as
documentation so everything is working
fine and finally we're having the edit
and uh so before that I'm going to just
show you how we can be able to add a new
task so when I click on ADD so I'm going
to add something in here just to show
how things are work in and I'm going to
just uh update the elements in here and
click on
ADD so as you can see the task has been
added successfully and I can be able to
update it of course so when I click on
update so we're going
to use the same dialogue but I'm going
to actually load all the information of
the test that we click on so I'm going
to add some stuff in here I'm going to
change some of the elements just to uh
see that everything is working
so uh as you can see uh everything like
the task has been edited uh
successfully so uh so this is what we're
going to be building for this
application so if you are interested
about building this application stick
with me till the end of this
video hi everyone welcome back so as you
can see I'm in Visual Studio code and I
already created the nextjs project so
I'm going to walk you through uh step by
step very quickly just to show you how
to be able to do this since a lot of
people know how to create this and if
you are new to uh this whole word so
don't worry I'm going to show you step
by step how to do so so uh the first
thing that I'm going to start from is
the uh nextjs uh website and uh so uh go
to the doc section so in here uh they
are showing us the STS needed to be able
to install nextjs so the first thing
that you should have in your system is
not JS so if we go to their website or
the page I'll just to show you uh what
it looks like so make sure to download
this and install it inur System since
nextjs use for the back end s uses uh
not J uh not
JS so after installing njs the next
thing uh so so that's the uh terminal or
the uh command line to install nextjs so
copy this and open up your terminal and
uh so I'm going to go to another window
so and just paste it in here and hit
enter so after uh hitting enter so you
will have the following prompts so just
stick with the default ones so we're
going to use of course typescript ESL J
CSS uh the Source directory I'm not
going to use it we're going to just
stick with the app directory for the
remaining uh questions just just stick
with the default options so uh then it's
going to install all the dependencies
needed to make sure that the project is
working so after doing this all you have
to do I'm start installing all the the
dependencies just type in npm run div
and uh you ready to go the application
is going to run so
uh as you can see my application is
already running and uh with the Local
Host 3000 so we will have this uh
default page provided by nextjs and this
is the uh code of it of course we need
to delete all of this code so we're not
going to need it so we're going to just
create uh empty div like this and we're
going to get rid from the
image uh uh object uh which is provided
by nextjs to be able to optimize images
so after showing you how to be able to
install nextjs so it's very simple the
next thing that I'm going to show you is
how to be able to
install um uh Shad CN so we're going to
go to the shaten
website so my connection is pretty slow
uh these days so I don't know why so
we're willing to uh load uh the page so
in the Shad CN so we're going to go to
the homepage so we're going to go to the
installation and the
nextjs uh which is the framework that
we're using and uh the first step we're
going to copy this and uh we're go back
to vs code and so I'm going to show you
uh what I did and what you would uh have
in into the terminal when you hit enter
so after doing this it's going to
install uh all uh so it's going to
verify next jss is installed J One CSS
uh validate the importas verifying the
component. Json which is this file which
is the uh core element of Shad
CN and then uh it's going to update the
ch. config.js and also the global. CSS
so if we go to the global. CSS so this
is the code that has been added by Shad
CN so to be able to make sure that um
all the uh the theme it's going to be
it's going to be unified inside our
whole project wherever that uh we are
using uh or whatever the component that
we're using inside the project and also
another thing that I did is I downgrade
it to the react 18 since still have so
you may have this warning issue uh which
is this one so to avoid this since I'm
not going to use any features or new
features from react 19 I'm going to
stick with the react 18 and uh to be
able to do this go to the package.json
sorry and here just uh replace uh 18
instead of 19 and also make sure to
place the types for the react to avoid
having some mismatch and some errors
with TP script if you lit uh the this 19
and you're using actually uh 18 react
version 18 of
react so uh this is uh the uh setup that
I did and last time I'm going to show
you since I'm going to use uh popins
font which is the Popin or the font that
I use for all my project so it's very
simple go to the layout. gs6 and add the
popins object from this package and here
we're going to create this concept with
this object and we're going to be adding
all of these
properties and we're going to add the
poppins. variable inside the class name
of the body tag and finally in the
global. CSS make sure to add the Poppins
class and we're going to use the
variable that we created in here so
we're going to use it by using the V
method and the uh CSS so and uh if you
want to use so I'm going to add here the
class popins which is the class uh that
we created and I'm going to add
something in here and hit enter and
let's go back to the uh actual browser
and uh so as you can see the
uh the uh font has been applied
successfully so this is how we can this
is the set of our project so the next
thing that I'm going to be that I'm
going to add in the project is the nav
bar bar so before we add the naar to the
application so the next thing that uh we
should be installing is the dark mode so
we're going to use Shad CN so they're
providing uh package to be able to add
the dark mode to the project uh if you
are using shedan of course so just go to
the dark mode you can go to the search
uh to the search bar and just typee in
dark
mode So eventually that's the
page and uh choose next shes of course
so this is the step by step guide to be
able to install the dark mode so we're
going to well so we're going to follow
all these steps here so the first thing
that we should be doing so we're going
to use since we're using the npn package
so just copy this so go back to the
terminal and I'm going to open up the
terminal and pasted the actual package
so it's going to be installing the
package for us so it's going to take a
little bit of time uh because of my
connection speed it's uh a bit low
so after installing the package as you
can see it has been install installed
successfully so now let's go back to the
page so the next thing that we're going
to be doing is creating this theme
provider uh which is a component that we
are going to wrap uh our uh body uh
uh uh tag in the layout. GSX so let's
copy this and uh so we're going to go
back to the app folder so here we're
going to create the file same provider.
GSX and I'm going to paste the code and
save the file so let's go back to the
page so the first or the third step as I
said we need to wrap the uh the
children uh with the team provider that
we just
created so uh what what I'm going to do
I'm going to just copy this and I'm
going to go to the layout.
GSS and I'm going to take this part I'm
going to paste it in here so we're
having this red line
because uh it doesn't know where to
import the component
so I'm going to add it like this so uh
vs code is going to do it for us to be
able to import the component from the
file that we created in here and let's
save the file so let's go back to the
page so we're going to add this uh
toggle so all you have to do just copy
this code so I've already created this
and just paste it in here so so I'm
going to do it
again and uh you will have this issues
uh these issues uh since it is uh
complaining about these components
because we didn't install yet this
component these components the button
and the drop down menu so uh let's do
this so let's go to the Shad CN website
and I'm going to look for the button so
all you have to do just copy this and
open up the terminal and hit
enter so uh it's going to install the
components uh so um I think I'm going
it's going to create a new folder called
uh components so we are waiting to do
this
so the button has been installed
successfully and uh as you can see we're
having a new folder called components
and inside of it we're having the UI
folder and this is the button. TSX
component so this is the main component
of the button and this is the whole code
so as you can see it's pretty lengthy
and uh all of this has been provided for
us uh to be able to uh to not focus on
the UI and just focus on the uh the
features of the project and make the
process of building the project lot
faster so the next element that we need
to install is the drop- down menu so
here I'm going to search for the drop
down menu
and we're going to do the same thing
copy this and so let me clear the
terminal and I'm going to paste the
command line and hit enter and it's
going to do pretty much the same to be
able to install a new component inside
the components
folder for
so our drop- down component has been
installed successfully and notice right
now we're having a new file and as you
can see uh the errors uh gone so uh
nothing uh so there's no issue in the
component so we can be able to call this
component uh successfully so if we go to
the page. GSS so let's delete this and
I'm going to add the
component like
this so I think that the name of the
actual component is the mode togle so
I'm going to just copy
this or just let me do this
and hit enter and if we go back to the
page so as you can see our our uh
component is uh working and our dark
mode is working so uh once we are going
to add the nav bar so it's going to to
be added at the right side so uh anyway
our dark mode as you can see is working
successfully so let's move to the next
part which is building our nav bar so
this is the header of the application so
it's very simple and basic hiter so
we're having the logo the application
the name so this is the name that I
chose for the application the button uh
to be able to add a new task and uh the
drop- down menu that I showed you to be
able to switch from light to dark mode
and vice
versa so uh so this is the nav bar and
uh also I want to show you how to be
able to change the colors so uh to be
able to do so so uh go to the uh theme
section and uh click on customize and
you can be able to choose any color that
you want so I choose the rose color and
uh click on copy code and copy all of
this code and uh go to the global. CSS
and just replace the default code with
the the code uh so let's assume that
this is the default code just delete
this and uh so let me copy this
again and paste it in here and save the
global. CSS so uh the next thing that I
did is I created a new folder called
components so we're going to be adding
all the uh components of the project
inside this folder and this is the file
nav bar
GSX so uh here so we are doing some
couple of imports so uh we're importing
this for the icon and the use team Hook
from the next team uh package that we
installed for the dark mode and I'm
going to show you why so this is for the
uh for the drop- down uh dark mode
toggle and finally the button so this is
the functional component the nav bar and
here we are uh destructing the use theme
to be able to access to the theme so you
can know uh which uh state that the
theme is in uh so uh so this is what
we're doing here so if the theme is dark
we are going to use this black uh this
background black color and the border at
the top and uh by the way those are just
uh tell utility classes otherwise it's
going to be background white so we're
going to use the background color and
we're going to paste whatever returned
in here inside the class name so that's
why we're adding the back ticks and the
kly braces to make sure that this is
going to be read as a variable not as a
string and those are just the utility
classes to make sure that this nav bar
it's going to have all the
uh all the uh styling necessary to be
able to make sure that uh we're going to
have this layout for the na bar so we're
having the width is fold and the height
it's going to be fixed uh the Overflow
hidden to justify between so to make
sure that these elements are going to be
POS positioned automatically like this
the pixel so we added some uh some
padding at at the left and at the right
and the bottom it's going to be we're
going to have some border at the bottom
and finally the background color that I
showed you so next we're having the uh
this component it's going to render only
the icon and the name so here we're
having the header tck with these utility
classes we're having this icon wrapper
so we're going to use the size 9 which
is a utility class
uh from uh uh chn CSS uh just to be able
to shortcut stuff without using or add
in more utility classes so it's going to
do this with and height with the uh 39
pixel each the background is going to be
primary rounded uh so it's going to be
medium flag justify Center and item
Center so you can be able to Center the
icon within this icon wrapper and this
is the icon on and finally this is the
name of the application so we're using
the H1 tag with all of these classes and
we're using the board in another spin uh
because the word task it's going to be
bold and this one it's not going to be
bold so and uh of course we need to uh
import this uh right here and finally at
the right side we're having the add task
button and the drop to down so right now
it's just a Buton because we need to add
the dialogue component for this so we're
going to do this later and we're having
the mode toggle component that I showed
you uh when we installed the dark mode
theme so we're going to import the
component like this and we are going to
make sure that these are going to be
within one div to make sure that these
elements are going to be positioned like
this automatically since we're using the
just y between uh the justify between uh
utility class so this is how we can
create the na bar and also make sure to
use the use client so uh it should be a
client component and because we're using
a use team hook here and of course we
should be able to import and render the
nav bar component so all you have to do
go to the page. GSX and import or use
the nav bar bar component in here to be
able to render it inside the uh homepage
so after we added the nav bar the second
element that I added all of these cards
these three cards so we're having the uh
so this is the design of each card and
also we're have in here the uh disc card
is going to show the total number of
tasks completed tasks and the high
priority tasks and also as you can see
the background it's going to be uh uh
it's going to have a kind of a slate uh
color uh so I'm going to show you how to
create this so uh first inside the
components folder so I created the stats
cards. GSX you can call it whatever you
want so here we are going to import all
of these elements so uh the first thing
that uh we need to do uh since we're
going to use the card component in our
GSA as you can see for each card so we
need to install the card component so
make sure to copy this and paste this in
your terminal and hit enter and you
should have the card. TSX inside the
components folder of Shad
CN and also make sure to install react
icons so uh Shaden uses the Lucid react
library but also there are some icons
that I love that are in the react icons
Library so so here uh just type in npm
install react icons so this is the name
of the library hit enter and it's going
to be installed
so uh after this we are going to set the
definition or we're going to define the
structure of each card so we're having
the title the value and the icon so the
icon it's going to be of react of type
react note and then we're g we're having
this array so for each object it's going
to represent each card so uh
normally uh what I should do here I
should add the single card
type and I'm going to add the girly
braces uh the bracket sorry since it's
uh an array so here we're having the
title the value and the icon based on
the def
that we created for each
card so after we created our array so
then we are going to uh use this stats
map and we're going to map through each
element and we're going to call this
single stat card and we're going to pass
for each object we're going to pass it
as a promp uh that I called single card
as you can see here and we're going to
take this promp and we're going to use
it inside the single state stat card to
be able to render each object and here
we're using some utility classes so
we're using the grid uh display and the
grid colum is three and also we're using
the media query just to make sure that
this is going to be uh dynamic as you
can see when the size of the uh of the
window changes so they are at the top of
each other so because we use the media
queries here here a little bit of margin
at the top some gap between each card
and also a little bit of padding and uh
here uh I'm going I'm going to explain
uh what's inside the single stat card so
we're having the main uh the main tag or
the main component which is card that we
installed from Shad CN so I did this so
you can be able to uh when I turn the
dark mode on as you can see it's going
to handle the changing of the color
automatically since uh it is used or it
is part of the Shad Cen
ecosystem so that's why I used uh the
card component so we're using the
utility classes here and we're getting
from the shadow so we are we added the
shadow non utility class or utility
class sorry so first we're having the
hitter and we're having the value so
here uh if we turn the light mode on
back so we're having the heer we're
having the name of the card and also the
icon so this is what we're having so
this is the name of the card and this is
the icon wrapper with all of these
utility classes as you can see it is a
pretty
long and uh finally we're having the the
value so we're taking each uh property
of the single card object and so we
could uh this destruct the single card
in a in a in a uh in a constant and then
we can be able to use it uh but if you
want you can be able to use directly the
single card object and use the
properties depending where you want to
place this into the uh component so this
is basically how we can be able to
create this and also make make sure to
use the use client uh to use the use
client to make it a client component so
if we go so let me save the file so we
need to import this in the main uh
functional component of our
application and uh here also I I added
the uh use team hook like we did for the
nav bar since if uh uh so here as you
can see the background it's not going to
be white so it's going to be uh this
color background slate and to be able to
uh to go with the uh actual ual next te
package that handles the dark mode so we
need to do this the same thing that we
did for the nav bar and here I added the
popins font and also the uh this utility
class for the uh for the for the height
and finally we're adding whatever that
we turn the background color constant
inside the class name to be able to
apply the color when we switch uh to the
dark mode or the light mode so after we
added the statistic course the next
element that I added is this uh cord
where we're going to be uh adding uh the
uh search input and also uh the table
and also are going to be adding the
dropdowns but first I want to just show
you how to create this and then we're
going to uh I'm going to show you uh
step by step all the other components
so um the first thing that we need to do
we need to install the input component
from Shad CN so again just
uh open up your terminal and add this
command line in here and hit enter and
you should have the input. GSX inside
the comp components folder uh sorry so
uh here if we go to the page. GSX so
we're going to have the tasks area
component
so this is the new component and this
component is coming from this file so I
create because we're going to be adding
other components inside the uh task uh
area so just to organize things so I
added the task area folder so we're
having the search input and the task
area so the search input so it's very
basic component so we're going to use
the input component from Shad CN so the
top it's going to be text I uh I made
the high a little bit uh uh so I I
changed the the height so to make the
actual
input uh to have uh the height a little
bit bigger then the place folder or the
placeholder filter by task and we need
to export this because we need to use it
instead the task area component so these
are the actual inputs that we're going
to use for this component so this is the
structure or the basic uh structure of
the task area so as you can see I added
some comment just uh to know
uh uh uh where uh like the structure uh
the uh structure of the components but
also I added these comments so this is
where I'm going to place the future
components so we're having the card the
card header and also we're having the
search input which is the component that
I just showed you and in this part we're
going to show or to actually create the
stat just drop down on the priority uh
drop down and here we're having inside
the button the reset button with its
icon so we're going to use this button
to be able to reset the uh filter and
also we're going to add here the drop
down view colum to be able to eliminate
or hide some of the col if you want and
inside the card content so we're going
to add the actual table by using CH
stack table and finally at the bottom in
the future we're going to add a
component called the pagination area to
be able to handle the pagination by
using Chan
stack and we are going to import this
component right at the bottom of the
main component which is the uh home
component to be able to render it like
this so after we created the task area
so the first component that I added is
this drop down so here we are going to
show the uh
priority uh uh TXS that the user filters
by and uh so when I click on here as you
can see I'm going to see this drop down
or this command component to be able to
actually select the priority that I want
so the same uh the same that has been
been used in the task component as you
can see so when I click on here so we're
going to have uh the um actual uh tags
that we filter by uh stages so now of
course uh I'm I'm I'm I'm just laying
out uh things how they're looking but
when we start working on uh using the
stage management and making the
application working so we're going to
have the just priority and whenever the
uh user clicks on here then we can be
able to show the medium or the high
depending on what the user clicked
on so uh the first thing we need to
install some components so here if I
open up the terminal so uh you can find
that I installed many components so so
the first component that we should be
installing is the command component so
this this is the component that we are
going to use to be able to show uh this
part so it is the command component so
make sure to just copy this and paste it
in terminal and hit enter so you should
have the command. GSX inside the
components folder next uh the next
component is the uh badge and uh
also um so let me open up the drop down
so we're having the command component
the popover component so if we go to the
popover
component so this is so the popover
component it's basically it's going to
allow us to actually open up the command
uh component right when we click
so we they're just giving us an example
just to uh show you what what it does so
just copy this command line and paste it
into a terminal and next we need to
install the
checkbox so go again into the Shad CN
website and copy this and paste it in
terminal then we're having the separator
and the badge so again type in here
separator so you should find this this
one copy this and P in terminal the
batch component so also we're going to
use the batch component which uh are
these two elements so they're using the
badge component as I'm going to show you
in the
GSX so here we are just importing all
the elements needed for this component
to be working so the first thing we are
Define the structure of each stages and
we're creating the array so this is the
area that we are creating so the objects
going to have the value the label and
the icon is going to be of Icon type
which is from the react icons
Library so this is the component so
we're having the open the set open uh to
be able to handle the opening or the
closing of the pop over so as you can
see we are going to add them here in the
pop over component so uh when uh the uh
open state changes it's going to call
the set open and implicitly uh so this
is the arrow function uh if we over over
the onop change it has
this uh this uh sign function signature
that has the open of tyoon so uh
eventually it's going to handle the open
and the closing of the component uh
automatically so we're having the pop
over trigger uh that is going to
actually trigger uh whatever that we are
putting inside the popover content so
I'm going to get into this so here we're
going to add this button so this button
which which is this uh whole element so
we're having the icon priority we're
having the separator and the Jacks so uh
here uh the variant it's going to be
outline uh we're not going to use the
default variant of the button and uh
we're have having the uh parent div here
so we're having the priority label with
the icon the circle plus icon we're
having the separator and we're having
the
badges and uh so this is for the popover
trigger for the pop over content inside
of it you can add whatever you want that
you want to show when we click on the
pop over but here we're going to show
the command uh components so if we go
back to the Shaden and open up the
command component so basically what I do
is I just copy this and I based it in
the code I'm just uh kind of tweaking it
to uh actually get the results that I
want but the most important thing here
is to understand what the code is doing
so first so this is the structure so you
need to follow this structure to make
this work so we're having at the top uh
the command component the command input
which is the input that we're having in
here so that's the input uh to be able
to actually uh search for the priority
that we want and uh here we're having
the command list and uh
uh like next to it we're having the
command empty so for example if it
doesn't find anything it's going to
return no results found so it is handled
for us by using the command empty tag
then we're having the command group
where we're going to be adding for each
to be able to render each item we're
going to use the command item so
basically the difference between here
and this component is because here we're
going to use so instead of just
hardcoding each object or each command
item and to make uh to make uh uh the
code uh clean we're going to use the
status. mop and then for each object
then we're going to use the command item
so this is why we created the status
array at the top so we can be able to
save some code here by using the map
function so then we're going to use the
command item so we're going to pass in
the states here as a value so we're
going to use the value property of the
status object and the value prop
property of the command item tag so here
we're using the class name justify
between uh because here we're having two
elements we're having this part and this
part to make sure that they're going to
look like this automatically we're going
to use the justify between and the
unselect property it's going to handle
the selection whenever we uh actually
click on the uh stages so if we open up
the log
so let's clear that out and if I click
on here so as you can see we're going to
have because I'm logging out the status
uh the selected States state so we're
going to log out the object that we
clicked
on but eventually when we are going to
start making this functionable all of
this it's going to be updated and of
course I'm going to explain everything
that I did and then uh so uh at the in
the uh left or the right part we're
having the checkbox so uh we're having
the uh status icon and we're having the
label at the left part sorry so and at
the right part we're having the number
of course this is going to be changing
as well uh when we are going to add the
uh statistic data which are the tasks So
eventually this is going to be updated
so this is practically uh the dropdown
the priority drop down that we created
and as you can see it is working
smoothly and it is looking uh good so
after we created the priority drop down
the next element that I added is the
status so uh as you can see we're going
to have the uh statuses that we want to
filter by and also I added this simple
drop down to be able to actually uh hide
or show the
icons so uh let's go back to the the vs
code and I'm going to start from the
drop- down folder so as you can see I
added the two files so this one for the
status drop down and basically we're
going to uh follow the same uh structure
that we did for the property drop down
so it is pretty much the same so the
only thing that we're going to change is
the
statuses uh area so these are the object
that we're going to use
and uh basically we are going to follow
the same uh pattern that we did for uh
the priority drop down so I'm not going
to explain this twice and uh you could
create one component and reuse it but
it's going to make things a bit more
complicated so that's why I added this
so it might be redundant for some of you
uh but just to make sure that think are
simple
uh so that's why I created it in another
uh
component and uh finally we're having
the view colums drop down so basically
this is the the actual uh component so I
didn't use the M function just to make
things simple but here I should create
an array and also map through each
element to be able to actually show each
uh each uh uh each item but uh BAS
basically what I did I just uh went to
the drop down
menu um uh website here and I just uh
so so let
me probably I took this component so
this is the component that I took and I
paste it in here I just Chang uh the
names uh
actually so uh we're going to update
this later on we start making this uh
functionable or the whole application uh
functionable so uh this is basically how
we created this part and this part so
the next element that we're going to be
adding is the actual table and the next
thing uh that I added as you can see is
the table so this is the uh final
version of the table so we're having the
task and the title the states the
priority and the uh date of creation and
the uh in this part or in this column
we're going to be adding the uh drop
down to be able to uh to change uh uh
some of the things in each task and also
when I click on the uh on the column so
we're going to have this drop down to be
able to uh sort Sly or desly or even if
want to to hide uh the colum uh so it is
the uh same if we go to the Shaden
website so the tasks so we're going to
have the same thing in here so the only
thing that is different is the colums or
the icons but it doesn't matter so the
most important thing here is to know how
this is
working so uh the first thing that we're
going to start from is this page data
table page
so uh they're giving us uh really uh
indepth uh sort of in-depth guide to be
able to install the tack table along
with the table component provided by
Shad Cen so uh the first thing that we
should be doing we should be installing
the table component and the tasta
component so make sure to copy these uh
command lines so I've already done this
so as you can see I uh added the table
component but also the chance stack
react table uh Library into the
project so after this I'm going to or
the first step we need to define the
data so since we're going to use only
static data we're not going to use uh
the uh the back end so the first thing
that I did I created this folder called
data and the TK data so this is the
actual data along with the the types of
the elements uh that we're going to use
in in each uh task so for the label so
we're going to use the union types along
with the literal types uh for type
safety so the label is going to be only
bug and feature and documentation the
priority is going to be low medium and
high and the stages are it's going to be
all of these uh literal
types so for each task so we're going to
Define it that way the task ID the title
the label the is favorite so if we go uh
back to our website or to our
application so we're going to have this
icon to be able to set a task as
favorite or not favorite something that
I added that is not here so just uh
something that I added into the
application so we're having the priority
so the pr priority it's going to take
it's going to be of type priority so to
make sure that the priority only it's
going to allow this literal typ so
that's why we defined this as the
priority and States so the same thing
we're going to use the status type that
we defined in here and the created date
it's going to be of type date and of
course the tasks area it's going to be
of type tasks with the brackets uh tell
on the types squ this is going to be an
area of type task that we defined in
here and these are the objects that we
are using using um to be able to show
the table or all the tasks inside the
table so this is the first step and the
Second Step so if we close this so uh
and if we go to the task area folder so
what I added I added the uh tasks column
and also I added the task table so let's
start with the task colum so if we go
back to their website so so the first
requirement uh or the first thing that
that they are starting with is the
colon. G6 eventually so it's a basic
example so but I'm going to um show you
what I did for our case so let's open up
the task column so it's it's a pretty
lengthy code but in
general uh for the so I'm going to
explain all of the uh functions and all
of the code in here so I'm going to
we're going to start from the task colon
areay and uh so here we are going to uh
to Define it as the task type um that we
created so for each object uh for each
object is each column so this is the
first column so we're going to use for
the header so the header property is
this uh part so we're GNA use the
uh checkbox and the name of the header
so this is what we're doing so we're
using the
checkbox and uh here we're going to use
the um the checkbox to be able to so
we're going to use the table uh
parameter from this object to be able to
actually select all of these elements
when we click on so to be able to do
this so this it's going to be so when we
click on the
so this is going to be triggered and
this function or built-in function is
going to be triggered to be able to
select all of these all of the rows and
uh here so we're having the cell
function which going which represents
each uh cell so here we're having the
task um colon sorry I I I uh I said that
this is part of the um of the checkbox
column but it's it's another column
which is this object and the next we're
having the is
favorite uh so uh the header it's going
to be empty and we are going to only use
the sell
function and uh here we're going to
access to each row and we're going to
extract the icon by uh using the row
that original that is favorite so if it
is true then we're going to use the star
icon and then we're going to return so
if this because it might be uh undefined
so if this not undefined then we're
going to use the icon with the size 14
and this is basically what we're having
says the row or the is favorite property
row has uh is true and we're having the
title so for the header we're going to
call the sortable header so uh here as
you can see all of these colons are uh
are going to have uh the actual drop
down to be able to sort it and to avoid
duplication the code as you can see
we're going to call the same component
called the sortable header which is
going
to have uh two uh Properties or two
props the colon which is coming from the
function and the label so and the same
thing that I'm doing for the states the
same thing that I'm doing for the
priority but if we go to the searchable
header so this is the actual code as you
can see so here where you you're turning
the drop down so if we click here as you
can see we're having the drop down with
the three element sentence sentence and
the height element at the
bottom so we're going to start from the
top as I said this is accepting the
colon and the label and this is the
definition of the prompt so the colon
it's going to be of this type and the
label it's going to be of type string so
first we're going to make sure that if
this is sorted and here we're going to
use the journey operators so if the is
sorted is true we're going to use the
ascendant uh uh if this is equal to
ascendant we're going to use this icon
otherwise else if the uh equal to
descendant we're going to use this icon
if uh the is sorted is not defined yet
so we're going to use the arrow up and
down um uh icon so the same thing that
we're having here because it is not
defined it so we're going to use this
icon but as soon as I click on here as
you can see this is going to be
undefined and we're going to have the uh
descended uh uh icon and the color is
going to be changing just to tell the
user which uh column that is currently
sorted and finally we're going to use
this hold go to be able to actually show
or render the uh drop down so here we're
going to add the uh the label here we
are going to add the ascendant for each
object so I should use a mob function so
when I click on the ascendant item so
here this is is going to be triggered so
we're going to use the colum that tole
sour chain so it's going to be true and
uh for the send in it's going to be
false and uh here we're having just the
icon for the uh the item for the hide
with it's icon so we're going to do some
updates when we start making this fully
uh functionable so uh let's continue
with the other elements so we're having
the title we're having the stages so for
the
stages first we're going to access to
the states icon so we're having this
function to be able to actually render
each icon based on these stages so if it
is equal to backlog we're going to use
this icon if it it is equal to cancel
we're going to use for this icon and the
same for the other statuses and here for
the priority icon we're doing the same
thing so we're using the switch case to
actually return the icon based on the
priority so because we're going to reuse
these functions
and uh so this is how we are going to
use them for the stages so we're going
to use this function and depending on
the stages that is coming from the row
it's going to return the appropriate
icon and we're going to save it inside
the status constant and we're going to
make sure since this is good be
undefined or null so we're going to make
sure that is not and then we're going to
actually use whatever the icon that
we're having in here and uh we're gonna
just return the uh stages inside the uh
span and uh so if we click on
here so we're going to show the stages
along with the icon which is this span
so the same thing that we did for the
priority just to save some time and for
the created ad so we're going to extract
the date of creation and we're going to
use the format date to be able to
actually format it like
this and the format dat it's going to be
uh this function so this is the function
that we're going to use to be able to
format date like this and finally we're
having this part to be able to show the
drop down for each task that we are
going to build so this is basically our
task uh table uh so the next thing that
we're going to be adding is the
pagination and as you can see the bottom
of the desk area we're having the
pagination so we're having how many rows
uh has been selected and uh we're having
this uh select component to be able to
select the elements uh how many rows
that you want to uh see in the table and
the navigation buttons to be able to go
from one page to another so it is the
same that we're having at the uh bottom
so the first thing that we should be
doing we should be uh installing the
select component by copying this and
paste it in your terminal on hden enter
so you should have in the components
folder so the select. GSX so this is
what we're going to use for this uh for
this uh part so uh now let's go to the
task area so I created a new folder
called the task pagination or the
pagination folder so we're having the
page pagination area so let me delete
all of this so this is the actual code
so we're having the printi so here we're
having the span tag to be able to show
how many rows has been selected and here
we're having so because this uh parent
St is separated into two components to
make sure that uh these elements are
going to be LED uh at uh the extremities
of each of the TBL so that's why we
added like them and we added the justify
between and the item Center to be
centered uh so so so that they can to be
uh centered uh
vertically so here we're having the pat
ination selection which is another
component so instead of just adding the
component in this uh soorry I created
another component called pation
selection and I imported it from here as
the pation selection component and then
we're having inside this div all of the
navigation buttons so as you can see
here I'm just commenting this uh when we
start working on the table and making it
working so we're going to use it uh the
table um the table uh object so we're
going to add it as a prompt so so just
uh to not lose this code so I'm just
commenting this out so when I start
working on this I'm going to comment out
all of these and it's going to work uh
so it so the navigation are going to be
working so for each button so we're
having four button and this is what
we're having so this is for the first
button the second button the third third
and the final
Buon and finally we're having the pation
selection which is a very simple
component for this
part so you can look at this how it is
working into the
Shaden uh into the Shaden uh or into the
page in the Shan website so uh what I
did just copy this and I just tweak
things so here we're using the mob
function to be able to actually see the
numbers like this so instead of
hardcoding each element
and finally we need to go to the task
area. GSX add the fer and we're going to
add the pattion area so one last thing
for the table that we're going to need
to add is uh the actual drop down for
each task so whenever click on this so
if we go to the
tasks uh to the tasks uh component and
when you click on here so we're going to
have this dro down so this is what we
are going to be uh adding inside our uh
project so the final thing in the table
that we're going to be adding is the
drop down so right now as you can see
we're having the three dots uh column um
or icon so when I click on it so we're
going to have this beautiful uh drop
down uh so it is the same drop down that
I used in here so the only thing that I
added is the icons so uh when I hover
over the label so we're going to have
plug feature documentation so we're
going to make this work but also I added
some color into the
delete uh group or the delete item so
let's go back to the vs code so uh first
the drop down it's going to be a
combination of two elements so we're
having this and also we're going to have
another drop down uh kind of for the
label so I'm going to show you how to do
this so here I created the task dropdown
folder so as you can see just to make
things uh organized so we're going to
actually instead of putting all the code
in one place so we are going uh we are
going to divide it into uh multiple uh
files so first we're having the constant
.ts so here we are going to uh add the
constants so this is the menu items so
uh here we're having all the objects uh
the edit the make copy and the favorite
and this it's going for the uh where so
this area is going to to be for the uh
label uh just for organiz and purposes
so we're going to store all of these
areas in one file so then we're having
the menu items the sub label menu and
the task dropdown so let's start first
from the task dropdown so here we're
having all of the elements uh that we
need to import to make this functional
component
work so here we're uh uh we're adding
the select label states where we're uh
whenever we click on the uh on the item
we need to store uh whatever that you
are clicking in to be able to use it
later on so this is the code of the drop
down so we're having the structure uh
the Shad CN structure so the drop- down
menu and the drop- down menu trigger the
button so here we're just adding the
three dots icon from I think from react
tons so let me see so this is for from
the react tons and then for the drop-
down menu content so we're going to use
the drop down menu group where we're
going to actually use the menu items
area that I showed you and iterate
through each object and you for each
object uh from the uh menu items area
we're going to pass or to uh pass the
item inside the menu item component uh
that I'm going to show you and then
we're having the separator which is this
one so all of these uh uh items are in
one group so we're having
the separator then we're having the um
we're having the um the label Sub menu
which is for the label so I'm going to
show you how this is working and finally
we're going to reuse the menu item
functional component to be able to
actually uh render the uh Delete uh
item uh so as you can see it is a
combination of sub sub uh or child
components so just for organ
organization purposes so I made it like
this so uh the first thing so you don't
have to create this from uh from the
start uh so first you need to create the
whole component and then shop it down
into sub functional component so this is
what I did uh so let's go first to the
menu item so this is the menu item as
you can see so uh it's going to accept
the icon the label the shortcut and the
class name so this is what we are doing
into the main functional component so we
are going to pass inside of the menu
item functional component all of these
elements so you can be able to use them
inside this menu item and this is
responsible for rendering each element
that we're having so we're having the
icon the actual label and also the
shortcut
and also I added this class name uh just
uh as an optional uh because we're going
to reuse this into the delete item so to
be able to actually change the uh red
color so that's why I added the class
name as optional into the promp and this
is basically the drop down menu items so
we're having the icon the label the
shortcut so want to make sure that this
is uh not undefined whatsoever so then
we can be able to use safely this drop
down menu shortcut uh element from Shad
CN so next I'm going to show you the sub
label menu. TSX so it's going to have
the value and the on value change so
we're going to add this as a call back
function so whenever we click on here so
this is going to trigger the on value uh
uh callback function that we're going to
use it inside the actual uh parent
component of it uh to be able to update
uh the states so we're going to work on
this but now I want to show you just
structure of the functional component
and uh so this is the structure so we're
having the drop- down menu sub and uh
here we're having the uh the icon the
label and uh here we are going to add
the or to use the label options area to
map to each element and use the uh drop-
down menu radio item so one thing that I
didn't show you so here when I click so
we're going to have the drop down or the
radio group here so whenever we are
clicking on the element so this is
basically how we can be able to create
the uh actual uh dropdown for each uh
task so so after we created the UI uh of
the uh main page of the application the
next element that I added is the
dialogue to be able to add the new task
so when I click on the button so we're
going to have this wonderful dialogue
and we're going to use Shad to be able
to build this very quickly so we're
going to have the title we're going to
have the status so it's a drop down to
be able to change the status the task
priority and the task label so we're
going to stock we're going to stick with
these labels as uh so since we are going
to work uh or being inspired from the
task component and the Shad CN and
finally we're having the close and add
new uh task uh button so let's go back
to the vs code to show you how I created
all of
this so the first thing uh so I'm going
to show you the structure of the files
so I created the new folder called task
dialogue and we're going to have the
main file I just called it uh uh task
dialogue and here we're having the subc
components for each element we're going
to put it in its own file so let's start
by the actual uh file so we're having
all the Imports needed so we're having
the dialogue uh the components uh that
we're going to use from the dialogue uh
component uh which uh we're going to use
uh uh in the uh following structure and
here we're having the separator the
button and we're importing all the
components inside the sub components
folder for each element so first we're
having the trigger button so it is a
button and then we're having the dialog
content so inside the dialog content
we're having the header so the title and
the description so we're having a
separator to be able to create this
separator at the top and then after this
we're going to create a div and inside
this div we're going to create all the
or uh add all the components so uh here
we are creating another div just to make
sure that these two elements are going
to be uh positioned in a grid position
and the same thing that we did for the
remaining Elements which are the task
priority and the task label so and
finally we're having in the future the
close button so it is a built in
component dialogue close so uh
eventually it's going to uh close the
dialogue uh automatically when I C click
on the close button and finally we're
having the add new task button so we
added it as a type submit since we're
going to WRA everything uh within a for
check so when we start working with the
react hook form library to be able to
track all the inputs and the fields that
we're having inside the dialogue so now
let's go to the sub components I'm going
to start by the easiest one which is the
task title so the task title so it has
so all of the components here have the
label so it has the label it has also
the input and also the error message so
this is what we're having uh we are
returning as a GS six so we're having
the label with these utility classes the
input and also the ptag so here we are
going to add the actual error so now
let's go to the second component which
is the drop down the task stages so this
is the file that is responsible for this
so here we are importing these icons we
important the task uh the task uh type
since we're going to use it so I'm going
to show you why we did so and also we're
using these component these select
components to make to have this uh drop
down so here we are going to create our
areay called statuses and this is the
top for each object the value and icon
so here we are going to extract all the
uh necessary uh uh literal types that we
created so if we go to the file so the
status it has all the literal types with
the Union types so to be able to extract
this so without having to uh use or
reuse the states we can be able to add
it just like this so we're going to take
it from the task type and we're going to
add the actual property within the uh
within the brackets and then we can be
able to access to all the literal tpes
that we created in inside the
stages so when for example just to show
you what we did so so when I did this so
it's going to uh actually give me only
the uh actual uh types that we added
inside the states so this is why we
Define it like this just for type safety
so for each value it has its own icon so
that's why we added the icons at the top
and here we are going to inside the
functional component so we're going to
create
uh a state where we uh save uh the
stages that we clicked on and it's going
to we going to assert the typ so the
same thing that we are that uh we did uh
that I explain so here it's going to
give me again the types uh so and also
it's going to make the coding experience
a lot easier and also uh you will not
run into uh into problems and bugs later
on when you want to run the application
so that's the power of
typescript so here we're having the
label and here we're having the select
component so here we're having uh the
value property and the on value chain so
whenever I click on uh one of the items
as I'm going to show you so the on value
change it's going to be triggered so we
are going to set the value parameter as
of type status and then we're going to
update these selected status with the
value that we changed with and then
we're having the trigger so which is the
selected value and then we're having the
content and uh so we're going to map
through each status inside the object in
within the select group so we can be
able to render each element so here the
value it's going to be the status. value
so the status is coming from the mob
function so we're having the status.
icon and also the status. uh value and
also we're add in some utility classes
to style our item so this is basically
how we created the status so it is a
very easy uh thing to create and also
the checkbox it's going to be handled
for the for us by the Shad CN logic so
now we're going to go to the task
priority so it's going to be pretty much
the same logic so let me close this I'm
going to save the file and then I'm
going to go to the task priority so as
you can see we are going to follow the
same structure so the only thing that is
going to be different is the priority so
uh and also the uh objects so we're
going to have just low medium and high
and uh as you can see the code uh
follows the same structure so the naming
it's going to be different a bit and
also as I said the prop so we're going
to use the
property uh the the priority uh type
instead of using the stages and uh for
the remaining code it is pretty much the
same and also for the task or the uh
tasks label so as you can see it's going
to be uh the same so the only thing that
is different is so here we're going to
xess the label property and uh for the
remaining code as I explained so it's
going to be uh it's going to be pretty
much uh the same so this is how we can
be able to create our dialogue so once
now we create the UI of of our whole
application so we're going to start
making this application uh
functionable so the next feature that we
are going to add is the uh search of the
tasks so here as you can see when I type
in um stuff so uh we're going to have
live search as you can see so because
I'm typing fix so I'm going to have the
title or the task uh that includes the
fix word and if something that has not
been found I'm going to have this uh
simple error so uh and also we're going
to use uh tack react table so um let's
go back to the vsod then the first
component or library that we're going to
be adding for State Management is
npm install zustan so we're going to use
zustan for State Management so uh so
we're going to use it for uh the query
since uh this part and another component
and this part is another component so uh
to be able to avoid using prop drilling
so we're going to use the state CH
management to be able so whenever we are
typing we're going to
save uh the character that we are typing
in a a qu in a state called query and
this stage is going to be used inside
the uh the uh task area where we are
using the react table to be able to
access to the query and actually do the
filtering so first I created a new
folder called called hooks so this is
the use quare store and this is how we
can be able to create uh a context and
then the uh in zustan that is called uh
store so first
we B the create uh element from the Zas
chent library and then this is how we're
going to create our store so I call it
use Query store so we're going to use
the create element and uh so here we are
going to define the structure
of uh the our store how it's going to uh
be so we're having just two elements
query and the set query and this is the
signature of the function and this is
the type of the query so it's going to
be string and the function is going to
accept a parameter which is query of
type string and it's not going to return
nothing meaning that's going to be a
simple function so the query so we're
going to set the default Valu so the
query is to be empty and the set query
is going to update the query which is
this one by using the set method which
is in uh uh provided by zent so this is
a very simple store to create with zent
so the uh next thing that I did I
created this function so this basically
this function is going to be linked to
the use react table
so uh so you will understand why we did
this function but uh the functions uh in
the uh react query so the filter
functions will uh accept uh three
arguments by default so we're going to
just use the row and the filter value so
we're going to access to the title by
using the row. get value and here make
sure to add the actual uh key that we
added in
the task column. GSX so so it has to be
the same key that we used so we're going
to because we're going to search by the
title so that's why I added the title
and the query so the query it's going to
be taken from the filter value so we are
going to uh convert it to string and
then it's going to be a lowercase and
we're going to return this whatever that
we're having in this manner so this
title function it's going to be used
inside the use react table so if we go
to the task area and uh if we go to the
tasks table so basically we're going to
be adding some of the elements here
inside the use react table so we're
going to be adding the colon filters so
these states and also we're going to add
the G filter row model I think this
function is going to handle the
filtering
and the on col colon filter change so
it's going to be linked to the set colon
filters and the state so make sure to
add the state object and inside of it
we're going to be adding the colon
filters so uh the actual filter so the
most advanced and the challenging part
in the react query table is the
filtering and unfortunately they're not
providing a very well uh organized and
very simple to use documentation so it
took me a while to be able to understand
and the way how they are engineering
this it's a little bit uh hard advance
and it's going to be overwhelmed for
many of uh people who just getting
started with this especially uh it it it
uses typescript heavily so it's going to
add uh a layer of
complexity so here we're going to add
the filter function property and we are
going to add the title fil filter so
this title filter so this is the
function that we're going to be
adding um in the filter functions so if
we go at the top as you can see we're
going to uh import it from the from this
file and also we need to add this
interface this title filter interface in
this in the
uh uh module so this is very
important to add
this and uh basically so I think that I
explained everything in here and finally
we're going to have this use effect hook
and it's going to be dependent upon the
query so the query it's going to be used
from the use Query store uh that I
showed you so here we're going to create
the new filters of type colon filter
State and just to show you how this
colon filter looks like in the console
log so let's me console log there
and I'm going to save the file so let's
open up the console
log so I'm going to access to the
console log Let's uh let's uh clear this
so when I typ uh when I type uh
something in here so this is the area so
this is the colum filter area so it is a
very simple object the title and the
value of the query so this is what we
are doing in the use effect so only if
the query is is changing we're going to
push uh the the object with the new
value of the query and then we're going
to update the SE colon filter so the
reason why they are doing it like this
uh like an area because as we will see
we are going to add two more filters the
stages and the priority so when we're
going to add the status we're going to
have another object with the ID called
uh status and the value it's going to be
uh these values that we are uh checking
in here while we're going to start
working with the status so once you
understand how this is working so you
can add pretty much any filter that you
want so it's going to follow the same
principles so let me delete this console
log and this is basically how we can be
able to create our first uh filter and
finally so this is something obvious we
need need to link the query and the set
query with the input so the value it's
going to be linked to the query and the
set query it's going to be link to the
onchange V listener of the input so when
this is changing so whenever we are
changing uh anything in the input so
it's going to uh change the query and
the set query and uh and uh by that it's
going to handle and actually execute all
the filtering inside this use react uh
table so next I added the priority
filter so uh here as you can see when I
click on low so I'm going to only show
the task that has the priority as low so
right now I want to just show the tasks
that have low and medium so I can click
on this as you can see we're having only
two task because they um they uh they
have the medium and the low priority and
also also we're going to be adding uh
the numbers to calculate automatically
how many uh tasks that are referring to
each
priority and uh when I click on reset so
actually the filter it's going to uh so
the filter it's going to end and also we
can be able to actually show only the
TXS or the filter and the tags like this
uh so as you can see everything is
working fine and also uh along with that
we can be able to uh as this filter is
working we can actually filter uh even
further by the
title
so let's go back to the vs code so the
first thing that I did I created a new a
new store so it's going to uh so for
this store we are going to actually
store the uh priorities that we are
checking and also we're going to use its
own seter so this is basically the store
so this is the interface so the check
priorities it's going to be of type
priority and the set check priority it's
going to be this signature it's going to
accept the priorities as a parameter of
type priorities as an array and inside
the store so the check priority it's
going to be an empty area first and then
this is how we're going to update our
checked priorities by using the set
method from actual uh zent so then I'm
going to show you how to be able to link
this with the priority drop down so the
priority drop down I did so many things
to be able to change the drop down so
the first thing that I did I got read
from the select priority so instead
we're going to use the checked
priorities which is the uh status that I
just show you inside the new
store and here we're having the open and
the set open so these values or these
states we're going to use them here at
the bottom of the pop over so now I'm
going to show you all the functions that
we're having in here so as you can see I
added some comment to not get lost and
also to know each function that is doing
so we're having the first function which
is the update D selection so this is
going to update the array whenever we
check an element so if we go to the GSX
we're going to start from uh the uh GSX
and the here so this function it's going
to be linked to the ons select event
list so whenever we select on the
command item so this is going to be
triggered and we're going to pass inside
of it the priority.
label so if we go all the way up into
the function so this is the label it's
going to be of type string so first uh
what we're going to do here some we're
going to do some uh typescript stuff so
uh because the label is a string so it
need to be casted as a priority but to
make sure that this casting is valid so
uh and to not run to any
troubles first we are going to create an
array of the valid priorities by uh
using the priority uh type so those are
only values that we're going to be using
and here we are going to check if the
label is part of the priority
so if it is uh not yet we are going to
exit the function and then we are going
to return this console log so uh these
are just top script stuff so it may add
a little bit of complexity to your code
but when you start working with top
script we will know why this is very
very
handful um and then we can be able to
safely cast the label as priority so the
first first thing that we are going to
do we are going to check if the element
that we checked or um so if we click on
low for example so we want to check if
this is include in the uh checked
priorities so uh if it is we are going
to delete it by using the filter method
otherwise we are going to be added and
here we're going to add this uh this uh
syntax which means that we are going to
just keep all the previous elements and
then we're going to add the priority
next to all of the other elements then
we're going to update the checked
properities by using the set checked
priorities so uh this is the function to
be able to add or delete uh so I'm going
to console log this just to show what
happens whenever we are I click
on the priorities so let me open up the
console log so when I click on low as
you can see I'm going to have an
array uh the low and the array so the
same thing if I click on medium so when
I click on medium again so it's going to
be deleted so this function is going to
handle this for
us so uh and uh this function uh we are
going to um count how many any tasks
that have the priority so here we're
using the use memo hook just for uh for
optimization so you don't you don't have
to do this because we're not going to
have a lot of data but just to know how
the use memo hook works so the first
thing that we're going to do we're going
to make sure that the tasks is if it is
empty or if it is null so then we're
going to actually just return the
priorities uh
area and uh then we're going to do our
counting so the counting is very simple
so we are going to filter uh the tasks
by their priority uh so this is for the
count by low so we're going to do this
and to be able to access to the number
we're going to use the length so we're
doing the same thing for the medium for
the uh high and then we are going to
return the uh actual values by using the
pro uh the priorities area. mop function
to be able to access to each element and
then we're going to use the switch
method so we're going to access to the
value of each property so if this is uh
low so we're going to turn the uh so
we're going to change the count property
by the state or the variable which is
the count by low so the same thing for
medium and the the same thing for the uh
for the high so this is going to be
dependent upon the uh task so the use
memo hook it's going it works like
pretty much the same like the use effect
hook but the difference here it's going
to return a value so then we can be able
to use this priority hook and if we go
at the bottom in the
um in the uh GSX so we can be able to
use it and actually uh access to the
count State because we added it in we
updated inside this use memo hook so
this is basically how we can be able to
update this and also inside the check
box so the check that's going to be
dependent if the priority that label is
included inside the checked properties
so since the checked uh is a
ban meaning true or false so this if
this is true so that it's going to be
checked otherwise it's going to be and
checked so this is basically how we can
be able to update uh the uh this drop
down and finally I'm going to show you
what how we can be able to just show the
badges or the tags that we selected so
here so this is the actual statement
where to be able to do so so we're going
to make sure that uh the checked
properties length is more than zero so
and then we are going to add the
separator and then we're going to use
the checked properties area to map
through each element and we're going to
use the badge uh functional component
from Shad CN and we're going to use the
checked property inside uh each object
and the check priority so this is going
to be uh a priority
type so I hope that I explained this so
as you can see it is a PR lengthy code
but uh you understand how this is
working even though that it seems very
easy to build but as you can see behind
the scene uh there is a lot of code to
create this and finally when I click on
the reset so it's going to be deleted so
all you have to do go to the task area.
GSX and here inside this button there is
set button so I added this onclick event
listener and all it has uh all it does
is uh it update the checked priorities
and an empty areay so we're going to use
this from this store that we created
inside the hooks uh folder so after we
added the priority filter the next
filter that I added is the states so
when I click on the drop down and let's
click on the to-do so as you can see our
filter is working and now we are seeing
the actual filter uh or the uh element
that we filtered by so when you click on
the progress so we're going to see both
tasks uh that have the prog the in
progress and the backlog and uh also
when I click on the reset as you can see
uh so the filters are going to be uh
reset and also I added more task just to
show that uh both priority and Status
are working so when I click on the reset
both are going to be reset reseted so
let's go back to the vs code and uh so
uh first I'm going to show you so we're
going to we're going to follow the same
step that we did for the priority so
meaning that first we need to create a
new store by using zent where we're
going to save the elements that we check
so uh this is what we did so we created
our interface so the check status is
going to be of type status as an array
and the set check status to be able to
update this state and here we're going
to use the create element from zustan to
be able to actually create our store so
the check state is going to be an empty
area array
uh uh by default and then we're going to
use the set check status to be able to
update this uh actual state so after we
did this uh the next thing that I added
is the filter function so I added this
filter function that we're going to use
inside the use react table so it is
pretty much the same uh function that we
did for the priority filter so the only
thing that is going to be changing is
the
status um so after we created our filter
so the next uh thing we're going to go
to the uh task area and also we're going
to go to the uh task table so we're
going to add some stuff in here so the
first thing that we are going to do
we're going to add the check status
array uh because we're going to uh use
it inside the use effect hook but also
we're going to use these status filter
the function that I just showed you and
here inside the use effect hook so uh
we're going to do the same thing that we
did for the priorties so we're going to
check if this checked stages. links is
more than zero then we're going to add
this object inside the new filters
before we can update the colon filters
so just to show you how uh this uh would
look like so if we uh console log this
so let's console log the new
filters and I'm going to open up the
console
log so and I'm going to click on this so
here as you can see uh we're going to
have our object and the value it's going
to be an area because we defined the
value as an area so when I click on
progress and if I go to the same uh op
object so the array it's going to have
the value to do and the end progress and
uh by uh with the use user react table
Hook from TX so it's going to do the
filtering for us so that's why we
defined this function inside the filter
functions property which is a built-in
property inside the user react uh table
and of course we need to add this check
stes as a dependency
so once we set up the filter logic
inside the react table of course we need
to update our drop down so whenever we
are clicking on the element here this is
what we are going to see and if we
uncheck this so uh the separator is gone
but also the tags that we un clicked so
uh uh and also we're going to use the
same logic that we did for the priority
meaning here first we are going to
import these States from the use check
status store and uh then we're having
this function so this update function
it's going to be linked to the on select
function so uh and also we're going to
pass uh down this function the status.
label uh to be able to know which
element that we click
on so the first thing that we're going
to do we're going to because we're going
to cast the label as stes since the
label is going to be string so I did the
same thing just to make sure that we are
safe uh we are going to validate this
label first based on this areay then we
can be able to safely cast it as a
status and uh then we are going to check
if this uh label that we clicked on is
included inside the uh the array the
checks States so if it is so we're going
to delete it meaning that when we
clicked on it so it's already Happ been
and the uh uh in the area so it's going
to be uh
deleted otherwise we're going to add the
actual uh
States and then we're going to update
the checked uh States so when this is
updated eventually and the task table
since this is updated because this is is
uh is added as an area dependency so
it's going to actually trigger this part
to be able to to by itself trigger the
filtering function inside the uh use
react uh
table so uh here so the count stages so
we're going to use it to be able to
actually count the uh the tasks that has
the uh filter back uh the status backlog
to do cancel and done and in in progress
and we're using the use memo hook
because uh you can't use the use effects
use effect doesn't return a value but uh
use memo hook uh runs pretty much the
same as use effect hook but uh it
Returns the value uh or uh it returns
something that we can be able to use to
uh inside the GSX so uh here uh we are
going to use this inside the chest X so
this is the area and uh in this area
we're having the latest updated values
with that we can use to actually show uh
the numbers uh here the real numbers
that are coming from the task area so
this is why we use this so the GSX is
pretty much the same that that that that
we used inside the priority filter so
I'm not going to go through this twice
and and this is basically how we can be
able to create our uh status uh filter
so after we completed the uh filter um
section so the next thing that I want to
show you is a little update in the data
so and also I want to show you when the
application is first loaded so we're
going to have this uh skeleton then we
can be able to access to the uh data so
the way how we're going to use the area
is going to be a little bit different
because we're going to simulate the
fiction of the data and we're going to
use the set timeout and also we're going
to use uh Zas jent so uh let's go back
to the vs code and uh just to show you
what I'm talking about here inside the
used tasks data store so uh because
we're not going to use the back end
we're going to just focus on the front
end so we're going to use set timeout to
be able to actually uh simulate the
fiction of the data so this is the story
that we are going to create so uh I'm
going to start from here because we can
be able to see the structure of our
store so we're having the tasks the set
so the tasks going to be of type tasks
as an array or null the selected task
it's going to be of uh so uh this one
we're going to be uh using uh for for uh
editing the
task so just uh like uh ignore uh this
one and this one and we're having the
set tasks to be able to update the tasks
areay and fch method which is a promise
of uh type void meaning that it's not
going to return anything so the task is
going to be first uh by default as null
uh so ignore this one and we're having
the set task to be able to update the
task that we are going to use in our
project and also we're having the fetch
tasks so here we're going to use the TR
catch block and as I uh said we're going
to use the promise of type void and then
after 1,000 uh milliseconds meaning 1
seconds we are going to update the tasks
array uh by using the set method with
the uh with the tasks uh with the tasks
area that is coming from uh the tasks
data uh the task data which is uh this
file so this is basically how you can be
able to Fitch or simulate the fing of
the data so it's a pretty
straightforward uh code and it's very
easy to set up so after we did this so
we're going to do some minor adjustments
in our code so let me close all the uh
tabs and I'm going to start from the
task tasks or I'm going to start from
the page. GSX which is the homepage of
our
application so here to be able to
actually call The Fitch tasks so you can
be able to update the tasks state so we
need to use it from this store and then
we're going to use this user fix hook so
whenever the uh home functional
components is mounted meaning that the
application is working then we're going
to call this uh this this um this
function and then it's going to update
the tasks uh state that we can be able
to use inside the task area. GSX so if
we go to this to this file again as you
can see we are going to uh access to the
tasks State and here at the bottom so
we're going to add this turn operator so
if the tasks is null so as I said as I
showed you it could be tasks of type
tasks or null so if it is null we're
going to call all the table skeleton
components and so so this is the actual
file uh to be able to create the
skeleton and also make sure to uh
install the skeleton component from Shad
CN so if we go here just type in
skeleton here and just copy this and
paste it in terminal to be able to
access to the skeleton components like
this so we're having the uh table so the
uh T head the table head and we're
having the table uh body so after
this so when the table is not null then
we can be able to or filled then we can
be able to safely access to the tasks
table uh
component and this is what is happening
in our application so first it's going
uh we're have we're going to have the
skeleton because the task state is null
then we can be able to access to the
table since the tasks is filled with the
data and also finally we're going to do
some minor adjustments inside the
priority uh drop down and the status
drop down so instead of using directly
the tasks from the static static data so
we're going to use it from the used
tasks uh data store so the same thing
that I did for the stated uh the status
drop downs so we're going to access to
the tasks
area uh or state from this uh store so
uh uh this uh I should uh did this
before I start uh you know creating the
filters but uh so I have to do this now
uh because we're going to rely on it uh
when we are going to add and delete and
modify especially when we're going to
work on this uh drop drop down to be
able to modify and update each task so
the next feature that I added is the
ability to hide the colons if you want
to so when I click on view and I click
on stages so it's going to be hidden and
uh also um we can be able to hide it
just from here and if we want to uh show
it back uh all we have to do just click
on the stages so there is uh there is a
a sync uh between the table and this uh
drop down but for the title we're not
going to be able to hide the title which
is the the the main element in our table
to be able to filter by and also to show
uh the
tasks so uh let's go back to the vs code
and uh so the first thing that we are
going to be doing uh inside the tasks
colum inside the specifically inside the
sortable header
so here we are going to add this uh on
click event listener colon. tole
visibility so it is a built-in function
from chq to be able to actually hide the
actual um column and only if the label
is different than the title since we're
using the sortable uh header as a
reusable function in every um in every
uh column every object so it's going to
actually ignore the title and do it for
the uh remaining um uh cols so after we
did this so we're going to do uh some
modification inside the view columns
drop down so uh here as you can see um
the actual file or code it's going to be
uh completely different so here we are
going to accept the table uh from the
print component and we're going to use
this table so because we're going to use
it uh in here to be able to actually um
hide the column that uh we want so we're
going to use all of these uh functions
the get all columns from and we're
going to use the dod filter colum to be
able to actually uh hide the uh
column so after we did this we're going
to call this component inside the tasks
area so here uh in the tasks area as you
can see we're going to use the table but
uh uh one um adjustment a big adjustment
that I did since we're going to use the
table in this component so because the
US react hook table is inside this tasks
table so what I did I uh took it one
layer up and I I put all the code that
uh handles uh the uh the change inside
the hook in here so as you can see all
the code that was inside so let me go to
the task table so the task table so
right now is uh uh is uh it doesn't have
a lot of code uh because we took all the
logic into the print component so and
basically what I did so instead of uh
using the data so we're going to use uh
the table so I just uh updated the data
uh table prompts and I added the table
in here and also make sure because the
name uh uh the names are going to be the
same for the table uh from the shadan
component and the type from CHC so I
named it as a Shad and table and I took
this and I put it in here into the uh
GSX so uh let's go back to the tasks
area. GSX and uh also I did uh a change
inside the data so we're going to use
the tasks so if it is null it's going to
be an array and the columns we're going
to use the tasks column from this file
so basically all the other code it's
it's going to remain the same and then
then we can be able to use this table
and pass it down to this drop- down view
colum component so uh this is basically
the change that I did to make sure that
the view or the hiding of the colons uh
work uh correctly so now we are going to
start working on updating the task and
the first uh feature that we're going to
be adding is to be able to make a task
favorite or unor favorite so here
depending on the state of the the task
whether it's favorite or not so we're
going to see this changing so because
this is already favorite so we're going
to have the in favorite but if we go to
a task that is not favorite so we're
going to have or set it as favorite so
when we click on it so as you can see
it's we're going to have this store icon
meaning that this is s as favorite but
when I click on the drop down again I'm
going to have the in favorite and if I
want to make this in favorite I click on
it so it's going to update the uh
favorite uh property and the store it's
gone so we're going to work on this
feature so first uh the uh First Step
that we are going to be doing so we're
going to start from the tasks Colum
GSX so here uh what we are going to do
we are going to use this function
because here uh so I already showed you
in the uh used task uh data store I
showed you uh the selected task so uh
here we're going to use it to be able to
actually store the task that we clicked
on in the uh selected task so we can be
able to use it to actually update its
value to know which task that we clicked
on so in the tasks colon so uh since we
can't be able to use a custom hook
inside the array so what we did uh we
are going to create a function and we're
going to pass down the task as a prompt
and uh here we can be able to actually
call the task drop down component so the
reason why we did so so we can be able
to use the set selected task so uh here
in the tasks uh drop down uh functional
component we did an update so we're
going to create these two call back
functions so when this is open so we're
going to update the selected task by the
task that is coming from The Prompt
otherwise when it is closed it's going
to be uh null and to make this call back
function uh working so we're going to go
to the tasks drop down functional
component so first we need to add the
signature of each call back function and
these callback functions are going to be
uh uh triggered dependent on the open uh
value inside the open on open change
event listener so when the uh when we uh
open the drop down so this it's going to
trigger and so if the open is through uh
then we are going to uh actually uh call
the open onopen call back function where
it's what what what is going to call
this uh as a result and then update the
uh selected task with the task that is
coming from its parent component which
is uh this part and when this is false
so it's going to do this the same thing
but now we are going to trigger or call
the on close callback
function so so that's uh the first
update uh that I did and the second
update is uh if we go to the uh menu
items. gs6 or let's go to its uh to the
main component which is tasks drop down
so here as you can see um I added the
selected task from the used task data
store but also instead of using the menu
items constant so then uh we are going
to use it inside the menu items area
State and with with it seter uh because
what we want here when we open up the
drop down we want to uh we want to
actually uh show the uh opposite of the
favorite state so if it is false so we
want to show this as favorite so when
the favorite is uh true we want to show
this as an favorite so this is what this
use effect hooks
does so actually we're going to use
directly the set menu items array and
we're going to use the previous array
and then we're going to Loop through
each item and here I added a new
property called kind so if we go to the
types so as you can see I add the kind
just to know uh whether we're going to
uh to uh actually uh uh click on the
favorite the copy of the edit or the
delete so I added this and uh also
inside the constant. TS so as you can
see I added the kind property so this
for this is the edit this is the copy
and this is the favorite so that's why
we saw the so want to make sure that we
are going to access to the element that
is uh that is for the favorite so this
is what the if statement does so we're
going to check if the kind is equal to
favorite then we're going to update the
object so uh here we're going to only
update the label depending on the
selected task so if it is favorite we're
going to show the unfavorite otherwise
we're going to show the favorite so and
this is going to be dependent upon the
selected task state
so after doing this um we are going to
go to the menu items. GSX and uh in here
we're going to call all of these
elements from the store and we're going
to add the onclick event listener so
whenever we click on the uh on any item
in here so this is going to be triggered
so uh this handle menu items click event
listener I added inside the .ts just to
organize stuff so those are the
properties or the components or the
prompts that we're going to be using for
this function and we're going to use the
switch method or case uh uh based on the
kind so if it is favorite so then we are
going to actually trigger all of this
code to be able to update the uh
favorite
property and here as you can see we are
going to call the update uh task so this
update task it is coming from this uh
use task data store so I added this
function to be able to actually uh
update the tasks so this is the
signature of it so it's going to have
the tasks as uh first parameter and the
operation and there is a promise that is
going to return this object but also
we're going to use this update tasks
function to be able to actually update
date the whole uh data when we want to
edit or delete but we're going to get
into this later on so this is the update
tasks function so we're having this
switch uh statement so based on because
we're are going to use the toast uh the
toast to be able to actually uh show the
messages based on the operation and here
we're having the try and catch block we
are going to use the promise and uh here
we are going to actually update the
updated tasks area that is coming from
this prompt and then we're going to
return the object which is success as
true and the message uh that is defined
with the success message depending on
the
operation so this is basically how we
can be able to create this so as you can
see there it is a bit complicated and I
had to uh update and adjust many things
but once this is set up it's it's going
to be very easy for us to be able to
work with the edit the copy and also the
deletion the label it's going to we're
going to add some code uh for this uh
because uh there is some logic need to
be added to be able to actually uh
update the uh actual uh features or uh
labels so after we can be able to
actually set the task as favorite or not
so uh two things that we are going to
add and the drop down so uh we can be
able to make a copy so when I click on a
cop make a copy so this is actually
what's going to happen so it's going to
be copied successfully but also we're
going to have this toast notification
using Shad CN so we're going to install
this and also I added the delete
deletion function so as you can see the
actual task has been uh deleted
successfully
but first I want to show you the steps
to be able to install the toast from
chat CN so it's a very simple uh process
so we need first to install this uh uh
component and then what we are going to
do are going to add the toaster in the
layout. GSX so if we go to the layout.
GSX uh here as you can see we're going
to put it under the children and it's
going to be within the theme
provider tag so once we did this then we
can be able to use the uh the
toast so we need to use or uh import the
used toast hook and then we can be able
to use it like this in any component
that you want so I'm going to show you
uh step by step how to be able to uh use
it so let me uh Delete all the tabs just
to show you everything step by Steps
step byep step clearly so the first
thing that I did so I did uh a change
inside the
.ts so here into the prompt so this is
the type of the toast so um and uh also
we are going to use the toast and the
toast toaster toast uh basically these
jpes I couldn't find them but I had to
do a minor change in in their uh file so
if we go to the
.ts so here I had to export so uh it has
not been exported probably they uh
forgot to add the export key keyword
here to be able to use the toaster toast
and uh also I added another uh export of
the type which is the toast type so let
me check uh or look for the toast so
there are actually a lot of uh there are
a lot of uh results so let me close this
and I'm going to find this manually so I
forgot where the toast type exists so
anyway
um so here is so this is the toose type
so make sure to export it because we
need it uh in here to be able to define
the structure of the toast and the uh
actual prop so as you can see we're
going to import the toast and the toast
toaster toast and to be able to get this
actually signature so here if we go to
the menu items so this is uh how we're
going to use the used toast H so all you
have to do just overover over this and
just copy all this
signature and just based it in here to
be able to use the toast which is a
function in uh this uh switch uh
statement so uh so that's the uh first
thing and also I did uh I added the kind
parameter inside the prompts of the menu
item so you can be able to use this into
and pass it down into the handle menu
item click so uh basically what I was
doing I was just adding than the
favorite but now it's going to depend on
the kind that is coming from the print
component which is the task drop drop
down so this is the actual menu item so
each item that we are looping through so
it's going to have its own kind property
so we are going to pass down inside the
menu item so we can be able to use it
inside this uh
function and uh after this inside the
this function so I added a new uh case
which is copy so uh basically when the
kind is equal to copy this is going to
be actually uh triggered so the first
thing that we are going to do we're
going to create a new concept called
copy task with of type task of course so
we're going to use the three dot
selected tasks uh to be able to just
gerine uh all the previous elements so
these things that are going to change so
the task ID so we are going to define a
new uh three numbers so we're going to
use the simple function to be able to
actually return three R numbers randomly
so this function I added it inside the
functions folder just to make things
organized for our project so if we go
back to the uh menu item or the utils
that is to continue continue explaining
the code here so the title it's going to
come from the selected task. title and
here we're going to add the
copy and uh finally we are going to
create to add uh to assign a new date
which is the current date inside the
created ad property so once we created
our object then we're going to add uh so
we're going to create a new copy of the
tasks by using the uh the spread
operator and then we're going to add
this new object and then we're going to
call the update task and we're going to
add in in it the added add copy task and
here we're going to add the copy so just
to remind you why we did the copy here
because in the function so let's go back
to the use tasks data store so for the
function as you can see here in the
prompt it's going to accept the
operation but it's going to be op
so that's why we used inde defined so
once this is equal to copy then we're
going to return this uh message so again
if we go back to the application and we
click make copy so as you can see we're
going to have this uh this uh message
and this message is coming from from
here so that's why we added in the .ts
we added the copy uh operation or
operator here and then we're going to
use the toast to be able to actually
show the toast and that's why we
actually Define it or edit inside the
promp and find the signature that I just
explained how to do so and here for the
deletion so when we click on the delete
so this is going to be triggered and
basically we we need to get uh rid from
the element that we want to delete that
we selected so we're going to use the
filter method and then we're going do
the same thing call the update tasks and
we're going to add the delete operation
here and finally we are going to return
the actual uh message depending on the
result so if the since the function
returns a promise of an object that has
the success property so if it is true so
we're going to use the default variant
otherwise we're going to use the
destructive and for the title so we're
going to depend again on the sex
property
to be able to actually uh show the title
whether it's successful or filled and
then we're going to use the delete
result that message that is coming from
the function that I just showed you so
basically this is how I updated the code
to make sure that we can copy and delete
the task that we want and the next
feature that I added is the ability to
change the label so when I uh um hover
over the label so uh first we are going
to um so we're going to have the uh
selected labels so when I click on
feature so as you can see the feature
has been uh the label has been updated
along with the uh actual chose
notification telling us that uh the
operation has been successful so let's
go back to the vsod to show you what I
did so the first thing that I'm going to
start from as the subl label
menu so here what I did I added this
onclick uh label item which is a call
back function to be able to actually um
get uh or take the uh the value that we
changed and take it up to the print
component so when we go to the print
component which is the task drop item so
as you can see here we're having the
onclick uh item label so uh here we are
going to link this to this function so
in this function this is where the magic
happens but first I want to just show
you very quickly the user effect hook so
this actually uh what it does it's going
to update the uh selected label so
whenever we open up the uh the menu so
we can can uh the um the selection or
the label it's going to be selected
depending upon the uh label inside the
selected task so now because it is
feature so we're going to have the
feature selected and if you go to this
task and we
hover so let me let me uh go to another
one uh so I don't know why this still
here so if we go to this task and hover
over the labels so we're going to have
the documentation label because this
task is labeled with the doc
documentation tag so that's the first
thing and uh here so this is the
function so uh for this part is just to
validate that this new label because
we're going to uh cast it so we want to
make sure that it's going it's valid uh
before we can uh cast this so and we are
going to check if the selected task and
the task are not undefined because this
could be null and this could be null as
well and then we are going to update the
uh label with the new label that is
coming from the promp of the function
and here we can be able to safely cast
this as a label because we already
validated inside this if statement and
then we are going to actually up update
the uh the task and uh here we are going
to create a new uh array and we're going
to use the M function and if the task ID
is equal to the task ID of the selected
task then we're going to use the updated
uh
task which is uh this one otherwise for
the other elements that uh uh that don't
uh
uh that uh uh don't have this condition
then we're going to uh their object will
be the same uh sorry for that guys and
then we're going to have the try and
catch blog and finally we can be able to
safely call the update tasks to be able
to pass inside of it the new uh array so
you can be able to actually update the
tasks inside the store and here we're
going to just return the uh message is
depending on the uh result so this is
basically how we can be able to actually
create this function so now all of these
functions are working so the last thing
is the edit but first before we start
working on the edit so we need to create
our uh so we need to create um so we
need to add the react hook form to be
able to actually um check all the fields
uh first and then we can be able to
create our function to add a new task
inside the
table so now we are going to start
working on adding a task but the first
thing that I added is the ability to
track the elements and all the fields
that we're having into the uh dialogue
so we're going to make sure that
everything is correct before we can be
able to add a new task and for this
we're going to use uh packages and
mainly the most popular packages that
we're going to be using is Zod to be
able to actually validate the schema and
create schemas and then we're going to
use the react hook form so it's a pretty
popular form to be able to handle a form
and also to be able to track the fields
and the inputs and also to handle the
errors for us and and then we're going
to use this packet so we can be able to
actually link our result schema with the
react hook form as I'm going to show you
in our code so just to show you a very
quick uh demonstration so for example
here we're having title is required and
uh if for example I click on add task
nothing's going to happen and the focus
is going to go back to the actual input
because there is still an error
but if I do this and uh I click on add
task then we can be able to actually
show the actual object and if I do an
update in one of these fields so just to
show that everything is tracked uh
correctly so let me uh clear out the
console log and and click on add task so
as you can see we can we are going to
get uh in the object all the fields that
we selected so once we hit the stage it
means that everything is great and we
can be able to actually use this to add
them into a database or an area as we
are doing for this particular project so
let's go back to the vs code and the
first thing that make sure to do so make
sure to copy all of these uh and uh uh
this is for result this is for the hook
form resolvers and this is for react
hook form so make sure to add these into
your terminal and H enter to be able to
install them so if we go to the
package.json here so we're going to find
them so here is Zod and uh also we're
going to find uh react hook uh
form so and also we're going to you have
uh the hook form resolvers so it means
that they have been installed
successfully so the first step that we
are going to be doing is creating our
schema so we're going to go to the
folder task dialogue where we're having
all the files related to the dialogue
and I created a new file called task
dialogue schema so here we're going to
create our schema as you can see so this
is how uh the schema is created using
zot for the title so it's going to be
string and
if for example if it is less than one
character so we're going to have title
as required and uh if we uh max out more
than 100 characters so we're going to
have the title is too long so we can I'm
going to just show you this so let's add
more
tasks so it means it shows that it's not
working but the most important think
that is working is when there is empty
so it's going to show us the title is
required so this you could ignore this
and we're having the states the prior
and the label so we're going to use the
enum the pchain enum function to be able
to
actually uh create the types as we did
for the label and the priority and
finally we're going to infer this uh to
be able to by using the type of uh
keyword to be able to actually extract
all the types from the schema and just
save them inside the task form data so
this is the first step then we're going
to go to the task dialog.
GSX and the first thing that we should
be doing uh we should be uh importing
the task form data and the task form
schema but also we should be importing
all of these objects from the packages
that we installed so I'm going to try my
best to explain what is happening in
here so the use form hook so it is from
the react hook form and we are going to
pass the task form data and then inside
this object it accepts the resolver uh
the resolver uh property and we're going
to use the Z resolver from this package
to be able to actually uh assign to it
the schema that we created so this is
how these pack this package has been uh
has been engineered so we need to use
this to make sure that our application
is working then we are going to De
destruct our method and right for now
we're going to just use the handle
submit function but we're going to be
adding other elements and properties
from the method uh as we move on with
the task dialogue and here on the submit
function it's going to accept the data
of task of type task form data and what
we're doing just here we are just
logging out the data and at the bottom
we're going to use the form provider so
uh the form provider is a provider that
is uh provided by react to forms you
don't have to create your own provider
and also to avoid using prompts when you
want uh because uh all of the uh methods
that that are coming from the use form
hook need to be uh need to be uh need to
go down to each uh sub component uh to
be able to avoid uh uh props so we're
going to just use the provider just to
make sure our code is uh cleaner so we
need to wrap so first we need to create
this form tag and we need to wrap
everything in between uh the form tag so
this is where we're going to use the
onsubmit function
and then we need to wrap the form tag
within the form provider so all the subc
components can be able to access to the
methods or all the properties that are
coming from the uh methods uh the
methods uh uh constant which is this
one so after we did this we're going to
go to the task title so let me go to the
task title and this this is how we can
be able to actually access to the
methods uh from the print component so
we're going to use the use form context
so to be able to to to to understand
this you should be familiar with the
context
API uh which is a built-in context uh uh
logic uh from react so you should be
familiar with this be able to understand
why we did so so here we can be able to
access to the Reg and the form State uh
and also we can be able to access to all
of these elements so we're not going to
need them for the task title and then
we're going to use the register inside
the input and we're going to use the key
that we
used inside the schema so make sure to
use the same to the same key that we did
that we created for our schema to be
able to actually track this input so
here as you can see we don't have to use
the on on on uh on change uh uh um
listener and we don't have to use any
states because everything is handled by
the use form hook and then we can be
able to access to the errors object and
then so because we are adding the task
form data since this is it accepts a
generic type so if I do this so it's
going to give me all the
properties uh that we uh that we created
because we're having the task form data
type we added inside the use form uh
context so this is a cool feature uh
with typescript and the react hook form
just to make sure that the logic uh the
logic is handled correctly I don't have
any bugs and then we can be able to
access the message that we defined in
the schema which is this one so this is
for the task title so uh the next
element I'm going to go to the task
label. GSX so here because we're going
to
use because we're going to use for the
uh selection we're going to use this
custom uh component that is provided by
Shad Cen so here uh things are going to
be a little bit different and to be able
to do so uh the react uh form Library
provided for us an object called control
so we are going to actually get this
from the use form context and then we're
going to create this controller object
which is also provided by react choke
form package as you can see and here we
are going to use the render method to be
able to actually render this custom
component from chaden and uh it is a
function that it accepts the field uh
parameter and we can be able to use the
field to be able to actually update the
state within this function so the value
is going to be field that value and the
on value change event listener so it's
going to accept the value parameter of
type task form data which to be able to
access to the label or to the uh literal
types that are coming from the label
property so that's why we did so and
when whenever this is changing it's
going to trigger this to be able to
actually update the field uh value so
the management of the stat it's going to
be done within the render function and
all of this it's going to remain uh the
same so here we need to use the control
uh which is the control that we got from
the use form context and for example for
the name if I do this I can be able to
access
to the key that we want because of the
control object that we got from the use
form hook which is coming from the
parent component so this is basically
how we can be able to actually track the
elements if we have uh uh custom
component and so let me save the file
and the same thing that we're going to
do for the priority as you can see so
here we're going to get the control um
uh object and here we're going to create
the control
uh tag that is coming from the package
and here so instead of using the label
we're going to use the priority the
control it's going to equal to the
control the default value is going to be
low and for the render function it's
going to be the same so the only thing
that is going to be different is uh the
elements that are associated to the
priority and uh so the same thing for
the stitches as you can see some is
going to get into this so uh there it is
following the same principle that I
did for the uh task uh labels so now
when uh after we defined or we installed
the use uh re use react form and uh Zod
uh then we can be able to actually
safely add the task into our
area so now when we
uh fill up uh the task title so I'm
going to change some of the elements in
these fields and click on add task so as
you can see we're going to have this
notification and also the task the new
tck has been updated
successfully and I can do any
modification that I want I can change uh
the label and can set it to favorite and
also I can copy it just to know that
everything is working as expected and
also finally I can uh Delete the
elements that I created so the same for
uh this
one so let's go back to the vs code to
show you what I did to be able to create
this function and the first thing that
I'm going to start from is the hooks
folder so I'm H uh I created a new a new
f function called add task inside our
used tasks data store so it's going to
accept as a parameter the task of type
task and that's going to return a
promise of an object uh success as a ban
and the message as a string so it is the
same uh it is the same return as we did
for the update tasks and if we go at the
bottom of the store so this is the
function so here we are going so of
course the uh function is going to be an
Asing function we're going to use the
try and catch block and here we're going
to simulate the synchronous operation so
here we're going to create a new promise
and this is the type that we are
expecting to return from the from this
uh promise and then we're going to use
the resolve method and finally we are
going to create the set timeout of one
uh one second second delay and then
we're going to actually update our state
by using the uh built-in property or
function set from zand so this is going
to be a function so I'm going to access
to the actual State and then we're going
to be
adding and we're going to make sure if
the task is not null so if it is not
null then we're going to use this turny
operator to be able to access to this
plug to be able to add the new task
otherwise we're going to stick with the
task that we currently having inside the
state object and then we are going to
return the uh the tasks uh property uh
in this object of this updated
tasks and then we're going to actually
return the resolve method or promise
with this object success is true and the
message it's going to be task added
successfully and uh finally we're going
to return uh the result and if something
bad happens we can we're going to access
to the air block so I'm just uh log in
this error and we're going to return the
object as a success as false and the
message failed to add the
task so also I created another hook so
it's very simp simple one to be able to
just open up uh and close the dialogue
store since we're going to use this uh
to be able to actually um so we're going
to use this when we click on the make a
copy button to be able to open the
dialogue so I need to create a a shared
state so we're going to use zustand for
this and so uh they're very simple
they're called is open and the set open
so also we're going to use this this
State inside the task dialogue. GSX as
I'm going to show you so this is the
updated code so here we're going to
access to the add task function that I
just showed you and here we're going to
add the reset function from methods so
I'm going to show you why and uh here
we're going to use the toast element
from the Ed toast and here we are going
to access to the is open and the set is
open and this we're going to use it for
to show the loading spinner that we
clicked uh on the ad task waiting for uh
for this to be added inside the
area so the is open and the sit open are
going to be linked to the dialogue as
you can see uh they're having these
properties open and the on open change
so this one is going to be linked to the
is open and this one is going to be
linked to the sit is open so uh let's go
back to our function so the first thing
that we're going to be doing so we're
going to update the is loading so first
I want to show you where we are we are
using the is loading so we're using it
inside this button so when the is
loading is true meaning that we are
waiting for the response we're going to
use this loader uh this loader uh icon
or spinner and then we're having the
addent task text
uh otherwise when it is fult we're going
to just use this add new task and uh as
you can see we're using the is loading
uh inside the disabled property meaning
that when this is true when we are
waiting for a response the button it's
going to be disabled as I showed you
inside the dialogue so and when it is
getting false then disable it's going to
be false meaning that we can interact
with the button
again so now let's go back to our code
to continue the code how we are going to
create our task so the first thing that
we're going to be doing we're going to
creating a new task object of type task
so the task ID we're going to generate
it by using again or reusing this
function that we created and for each
element uh it's going to be linked to
the property that we used for the task
type so the is favorite it's going to be
by default false and and the created add
property we're going to use the new date
to be able to create a date of this
current time and then we're going to use
the try and catch block so we're going
to actually access or call the add task
which is an Asing function so that's why
we we use the weight and here as you can
see we're using the ins saying function
because you can't use the weight keyword
within a function and the function is
still synchronous so it needs to be in
synchronous and then we are going to
take this new task and put it in the add
task since it is acceped a prompt and
then we're going to show the toast
notification based on the results by
using the chain operator so if it is
success we're going to use the default
variant if it is not we're going to use
the destructive variant so the title
it's going to be result. success and
here we're going to show the description
so if this is true we're going to show
this with the new task. ID as you
noticed otherwise we're going to show
the fail to add the task message and the
description it's going to be uh the
result that message that is coming from
the add task function and finally we're
going to use the reset so because when
we click on the add task the window is
closed so we're using the set open as
false and the fields are not being empty
to be able to force being empty we're
going to use the re reset me method from
the react to form Library otherwise if
there is an error we're going to
actually access to this block and
finally the S is loading it's going to
be false to
actually set this is loading back to its
default state so this is how we can be
able to create our task so one last
thing that I need to add is modifying
the TK